<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Zoltán's Blog</title><link>https://bzoltan1.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on Zoltán's Blog</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>zoltan.balogh@suse.com (Zoltán Balogh)</managingEditor><webMaster>zoltan.balogh@suse.com (Zoltán Balogh)</webMaster><copyright>© Zoltán Balogh 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 05:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://bzoltan1.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Redmine RAG system</title><link>https://bzoltan1.github.io/redmine-rag-system/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 05:00:00 +0200</pubDate><author>zoltan.balogh@suse.com (Zoltán Balogh)</author><guid>https://bzoltan1.github.io/redmine-rag-system/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="the-goal">The Goal&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The goal was to extract all issues from a Redmine instance, anonymize the data, and build a local RAG system for semantic search and Q&amp;amp;A.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Just like with the previous experiment with Bugzilla it started with data extraction. I planned to make a simple bulk download via Redmine API. Then came the first problem. Redmine&amp;rsquo;s API doesn&amp;rsquo;t return journal entries (comments) when using the project-level endpoint, even with the include=journals parameter. I tried out different ways but nothing worked. The solution was, after all, to change the strategy and fetch each issue individually via /issues/{id}.json. This was much slower but guaranteed complete data including all comments.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>I want to have a hot shower</title><link>https://bzoltan1.github.io/i-want-to-have-a-hot-shower/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 05:00:00 +0200</pubDate><author>zoltan.balogh@suse.com (Zoltán Balogh)</author><guid>https://bzoltan1.github.io/i-want-to-have-a-hot-shower/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="it-all-started-last-summer">It all started last summer&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>When my family moved to a new place. In our previous home we had a district heating service that included unlimited hot water for a fixed price. That was awesome - not very environmentally friendly and actually not very cheap, but we never ran out of hot water.&lt;/p>


&lt;div class="box" style="max-width:50%">
 &lt;figure itemprop="associatedMedia" itemscope itemtype="http://schema.org/ImageObject">
 &lt;div class="img">
 &lt;img itemprop="thumbnail" src="https://bzoltan1.github.io/the-boiler.jpg" alt="The boiler"/>
 &lt;/div>
 &lt;a href="https://bzoltan1.github.io/the-boiler.jpg" itemprop="contentUrl">&lt;/a>
 &lt;/figure>
&lt;/div>

&lt;p>In our new home we are independent from the city&amp;rsquo;s hot water services. This is good because we pay exactly for the energy we use. It means that we have a 300-liter hot water heater that we turn on when we want to make as much hot water as we need. In most households such a hot water boiler has a thermostat set to a specific temperature and the heater keeps all 300 liters of water as hot as it is set. I do not like this, because regardless of how great the insulation on the water tank is, it loses temperature over time. I needed a smarter system.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Building a Local Bugzilla RAG System</title><link>https://bzoltan1.github.io/building-a-local-bugzilla-rag-system/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 10:00:00 +0200</pubDate><author>zoltan.balogh@suse.com (Zoltán Balogh)</author><guid>https://bzoltan1.github.io/building-a-local-bugzilla-rag-system/</guid><description>&lt;p>My goal was to build a local database that could:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Ingest my ~4GB Bugzilla database&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Answer questions or give advice on new bugs based on historical ones&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Run offline on my openSUSE Tumbleweed machine, which is equipped with 64GB RAM and an AMD Ryzen 7 PRO 7840U&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Naturally, my first idea was to build a standalone LLM like GPT. But fine-tuning an LLM on custom data is resource-intensive—a massive understatement. When I started to fine-tune an LLM on my laptop, I let the process run for a full week, and it reached only 1%. Using cloud-based services or investing in powerful new hardware were not options. Also, the problem with standalone LLMs is that they may hallucinate or generate inaccurate information, especially on domain-specific topics. The other disadvantage of using LLMs is that they are static; once trained, they don&amp;rsquo;t know anything that happened afterward.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Paradigm shifts in software development</title><link>https://bzoltan1.github.io/paradigm-shifts-in-software-development/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 06:13:44 +0300</pubDate><author>zoltan.balogh@suse.com (Zoltán Balogh)</author><guid>https://bzoltan1.github.io/paradigm-shifts-in-software-development/</guid><description>&lt;p>I could have given it the title &amp;lsquo;Old Man&amp;rsquo;s Ranting,&amp;rsquo; but even though it would have been more honest, it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be very catchy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="why-i-decided-to-write-this-up">Why I decided to write this up?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://bzoltan1.github.io/kala-patagonico.jpeg" alt="Kala Patagónico">
I knew something was in the air when my favorite fishmonger, an incredibly friendly and always super-helpful fellow, asked me what I thought about that Chat.GPT thingy. That doesn&amp;rsquo;t happen often. Like our neighbor, who was a fantastic craftsman, didn&amp;rsquo;t stop me in the &amp;rsquo;90s to ask me what I thought about object-oriented programming. Neither did the ladies in our university&amp;rsquo;s canteen ask us how POSIX threads would impact software engineering. Sure, the significance of these examples is arguable. Still, my point is that a massive paradigm shift in our beloved profession rarely breaks through to the general public.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Cross build and packaging</title><link>https://bzoltan1.github.io/cross-build-and-packaging/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2023 03:27:12 +0300</pubDate><author>zoltan.balogh@suse.com (Zoltán Balogh)</author><guid>https://bzoltan1.github.io/cross-build-and-packaging/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s start by clarifying what we mean by cross-building and cross-packaging. Cross-compilation is the process of compiling source code on one platform, called the host, in order to generate an executable binary for a different target platform. The emphasis here is on the word &amp;ldquo;different&amp;rdquo;. The target platform may have a different CPU architecture, such as when we work on an x86 computer and want to build software for a Raspberry Pi board with an ARM CPU. But even if the target platform has the same CPU architecture as the host, there may be several other possible differences. For example, the host may be running &lt;a href="https://wiki.debian.org/DebianUnstable">Debian Sid&lt;/a>, while the target may be running &lt;a href="https://www.opensuse.org/#Leap">openSUSE Leap&lt;/a>. Different Linux distributions may have different compilers, linkers, and run-time libraries. Even when using the same distribution as the host for the target, they may be different releases, such as openSUSE Tumbleweed and Leap. In short, nothing guarantees that the target system will have the same shared libraries as the host system.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Reverse dependencies</title><link>https://bzoltan1.github.io/reverse-dependencies/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 19:15:12 +0300</pubDate><author>zoltan.balogh@suse.com (Zoltán Balogh)</author><guid>https://bzoltan1.github.io/reverse-dependencies/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="as-start-lets-sort-it-out-what-is-dependency-and-what-is-reverse-dependency">As start let&amp;rsquo;s sort it out what is dependency and what is reverse dependency.&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Dependencies and reverse dependencies in Linux distributions are important concepts to understand. A package dependency means that another package relies on it in order to function. For example, if package B requires package A to be installed in order to work, then package B is dependent on package A and is considered a reverse dependency of package A.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Build system statistics</title><link>https://bzoltan1.github.io/build-system-statistics/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 04:41:11 +0300</pubDate><author>zoltan.balogh@suse.com (Zoltán Balogh)</author><guid>https://bzoltan1.github.io/build-system-statistics/</guid><description>&lt;p>From time to time we should ask ourselves how are we doing. Are we successful, are we on the right track, are we heading to the right direction, are we fast enough, are we accelerating or slowing down?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This time I am talking about the openSUSE Linux Distribution and about the SUSE Linux Enterprise Server.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And here I quickly would like to note an important disclaimer with a short story.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Checking changelogs with zypper</title><link>https://bzoltan1.github.io/checking-changelogs-with-zypper/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 11:11:11 +0300</pubDate><author>zoltan.balogh@suse.com (Zoltán Balogh)</author><guid>https://bzoltan1.github.io/checking-changelogs-with-zypper/</guid><description>&lt;p>I have heard way to often the question from Linux and specially SUSE Linux users that &lt;em>&amp;ldquo;How can I check the changelog of a package or new version of a package available on the repository, but not yet installed&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There was no easy answer for that question, so I have decided to make a little tool for that.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="how-it-is-done">How it is done&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>All the enabled repositories have a bunch of configuration files in a well structured directory tree under the &lt;code>/var/cache/zypp/raw/&lt;/code>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Data visualization with Grafana and Telegraf</title><link>https://bzoltan1.github.io/data-visualization-with-grafana-and-telegraf/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 20:32:50 +0300</pubDate><author>zoltan.balogh@suse.com (Zoltán Balogh)</author><guid>https://bzoltan1.github.io/data-visualization-with-grafana-and-telegraf/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="it-all-started-when">It all started when&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Few weeks ago we have decided to create a dashboard where we can monitor the status of the SUSE Linux Enterprise maintenance update queue. Naturally there are tons of cool open source solutions to build this type of monitoring. Two decades ago I probably would have written a Perl or Python based monitoring script for the monitoring part and use the good old gnuplot (&lt;a href="http://www.gnuplot.info/">http://www.gnuplot.info/&lt;/a>) to visualize the data and create an active page written in some silly web UI framework. Let&amp;rsquo;s just say that luckily those times has passed.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Audio controlled Shelly devices</title><link>https://bzoltan1.github.io/audio-controlled-shelly-devices/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2022 17:32:50 +0300</pubDate><author>zoltan.balogh@suse.com (Zoltán Balogh)</author><guid>https://bzoltan1.github.io/audio-controlled-shelly-devices/</guid><description>&lt;p>The idea came from &lt;a href="https://github.com/perlpunk">Tina Müller&lt;/a> who was giving and awesome demo of the Vosk library. I quickly checked out the &lt;a href="https://alphacephei.com/vosk/">Alphacephei&lt;/a> pages.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I fundamentally like when a cool library has Python APIs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Vosk is an offline open source speech recognition toolkit. It enables speech recognition for lots of languages. The vosk models are small (50 Mb) but still provide continuous large vocabulary transcription, zero-latency response with streaming API.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Installing vosk library on my openSUSE Tumbleweed goes like&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Contributing to SLE/openSUSE</title><link>https://bzoltan1.github.io/contributing-to-sle/opensuse/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2022 06:42:50 +0300</pubDate><author>zoltan.balogh@suse.com (Zoltán Balogh)</author><guid>https://bzoltan1.github.io/contributing-to-sle/opensuse/</guid><description>&lt;p>The motivation of this post is to demonstrate how easy and logical is the workflow of an upstream change in a project to a given SUSE Linux codestream. I try to write this post in a codestream agnostic way. As I have experienced the workflow from the package maintainer point of view is the same for SUSE:SLE-15:Update and for openSUSE:Factory.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-i-want-to-do">What I want to do&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>It all starts with a Bugzilla case. For the sake of this exercise I will walk through the process with this bug report: &lt;a href="https://bugzilla.suse.com/show_bug.cgi?id=1195126">https://bugzilla.suse.com/show_bug.cgi?id=1195126&lt;/a> I use this case because it was a fairly simple, straight forward issue. It is a CVE-2022-0351: vim: uncontrolled recursion in eval7(). This is a Common Vulnerabilities and Exposures (CVE) what means that somebody has found and published an information-security vulnerabilities and exposures. By classification it is an important issue and as a package maintainer it is not my role to re-evaluate if the issue represents serious threat or not. My goal is to figure out if I can reproduce the issue and if I can find a fix for it.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Playing with Shelly</title><link>https://bzoltan1.github.io/playing-with-shelly/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 10:35:50 +0300</pubDate><author>zoltan.balogh@suse.com (Zoltán Balogh)</author><guid>https://bzoltan1.github.io/playing-with-shelly/</guid><description>&lt;p>For xmass I got few Shelly lamps to play with. Shelly lamps are simple IoT devices. Super easy to install, configure and use. The Youtube is full with instructions on what can be done with these smart lamps.
Naturally my main motivation was to figure out how to hack these devices and how ready my openSUSE servers are with tools and services (spoiler: they are ready)&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="look-daddy-no-cloud">Look daddy no cloud&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Needless to say that like most smart home automation devices the Shelly lamps can be operated via the Shelly cloud. I may cover that area in the next post. But now I am interested in what can be done without the cloud. After all, one big selling point of the Shelly devices is that they are fully operable and functional even without Internet connection just on a WiFi LAN. It means that if I am concerned about the security of my home infrastructure I have an option not to expose my smart devices.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Measuring web traffic with Matomo</title><link>https://bzoltan1.github.io/measuring-web-traffic-with-matomo/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2021 20:40:57 +0300</pubDate><author>zoltan.balogh@suse.com (Zoltán Balogh)</author><guid>https://bzoltan1.github.io/measuring-web-traffic-with-matomo/</guid><description>&lt;p>Matomo is an open source PHP/MySQL  based web analytics application to track online visits to websites and displays reports on these visits. It does what Google Analytics does, but it is open source. Matomo has commercial cloud based offering for those who do not want to host their own instance but the code is there on GitHub (&lt;a href="https://github.com/matomo-org/matomo">https://github.com/matomo-org/matomo&lt;/a>) for anyone who is interested.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I decided to first test drive the cloud based solution and then install my own instance. &lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Private cloud based on openSUSE Leap 15.3 beta and Nextcloud</title><link>https://bzoltan1.github.io/private-cloud-based-on-opensuse-leap-15.3-beta-and-nextcloud/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 19:36:57 +0300</pubDate><author>zoltan.balogh@suse.com (Zoltán Balogh)</author><guid>https://bzoltan1.github.io/private-cloud-based-on-opensuse-leap-15.3-beta-and-nextcloud/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="motivation">Motivation&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I used to have a Synology DS414 server what worked  well for about 8 years. Naturally, occasionally I had to change disks in the RAID5 system in it, but other than that it did its job. But regardless of the really smooth user experience and the low maintenance needs I never really liked that system as the Synology Disk Station Manager OS is not like many &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; Linux distributions and the community behind that OS is basically non existent. And to be honest I do not really feel that Synology is very eager to build and maintain a community around their OS. It looks more like that they just barely comply with the GPL. All in all, I had just enough motivation to migrate my private cloud and NAS to a proper OS.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Setup a Blog With Github Pages and Hugo</title><link>https://bzoltan1.github.io/setup-a-blog-with-github-pages-and-hugo/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 19:36:57 +0300</pubDate><author>zoltan.balogh@suse.com (Zoltán Balogh)</author><guid>https://bzoltan1.github.io/setup-a-blog-with-github-pages-and-hugo/</guid><description>&lt;p>GitHub pages are super powerful and very easy to use for creating markdown based static websites.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this post I will walk through how I made this very page.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My setup will be two GitHub repositories, one for the source of the page (&lt;a href="https://github.com/bzoltan1/blog-source">https://github.com/bzoltan1/blog-source&lt;/a>) and the other where the html artifacts are deployed (&lt;a href="https://github.com/bzoltan1/bzoltan1.github.io">https://github.com/bzoltan1/bzoltan1.github.io&lt;/a>)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here I would like to note that it is possible to use a single repository with two branches, one for holding the the source and the other where the website is deployed. I just personally find the two repository setup more elegant without any particular reason.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Telegram Bridge</title><link>https://bzoltan1.github.io/telegram-bridge/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 19:36:57 +0300</pubDate><author>zoltan.balogh@suse.com (Zoltán Balogh)</author><guid>https://bzoltan1.github.io/telegram-bridge/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="motivation">Motivation&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I got lucky with my original hackweek project and I have managed to set up my Leap 15.3 based NAS and private cloud running on NextCloud earlier than planned.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So I though that as an extra project I will set up a proper system monitoring service. The monit service is very handy (thanks for the idea to Paolo Stivanin) but by default it wants to send emails when something goes wrong. Instead of emails I would prefer a real instant message. I am using mostly Telegram for personal purposes. Sure I am using Signal, Matrix, Slack and Rocket.Chat too and technically I have WhatsApp account too. But I decided to start with Telegram.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>About Zoltán</title><link>https://bzoltan1.github.io/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>zoltan.balogh@suse.com (Zoltán Balogh)</author><guid>https://bzoltan1.github.io/about/</guid><description>&lt;p>There are few more identites what are definitely not covered here.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="looking-back">Looking back&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Press some of my (social) buttons to find out more.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>